[Music]
hi there my name is Tom blumfield I'm a
group partner at Y combinator and today
we're going to be talking about one of
my favorite topics metrics and why
they're so useful for startups so why
are metrics important first of all it's
pretty obvious that with better metrics
you'll make better decisions it's like
flying an airplane with no instrument
you're Flying Blind you don't know
what's happening to the aircraft and
you're not in control having great
metrics is like having great instruments
in an aircraft it lets you tweak and
iterate and make sure you're really in
control of your startup we often see and
I've seen in even in the last two or
three weeks Founders who've had these
great launches they've launched on
Hacker News on product hunt and they've
had hundreds of people come and use
their service day after day but they
have no idea how many of those news
users are new users or returning users
they don't know if they're daily active
or weekly active they could be churning
off all of their users instantly and
they don't know at all so the first
thing they do after launching blind is
to go back and build metrics in we would
advise you don't do that you should
build basic metrics into a product
before you launch and as an investor
it's really easy to tell Founders who
are in command of their metrics versus
Founders who aren't and it's really
impressive when founders can talk about
what percentage best signups are da or W
or what the annual revenue per user is
and we'll go into some of these in
detail but it's a big differentiator
when a Founder can talk so fluently
about these metrics before we dive in I
want to give a couple of warnings The
Other Extreme is also bad so it's a
Founder who even before they launched
has a dashboard with perhaps 500 metrics
maybe they've been a product manager at
a big tech company or they've just
watched too many YouTube videos but they
want to make every decision in their
startup with metrics and when you have
only have a few hundred or a few
thousand users that's basically
impossible you know they want to split
test everything should this button be
blue or green and frankly it doesn't
matter and you don't have the volume of
users or data to make those kind of
split tests sensibly so what you should
do is certainly split test the really
important decisions you know should the
cost per user be $80 per year or $200
per year that's a really good experiment
to split test but you know making
buttons red or green that's not really
something you have the scale to split
test until you're really at the the size
of Google or Facebook a final warning
don't hide behind your metrics you've
still got to get out of the building and
talk to customers Brian from Airbnb
still hosts Airbnb users in his home
it's an obsession with staying close to
customers so you can't let metrics get
in the way of that so let's get started
you're planning a product launch in
perhaps a week or two and maybe maybe
you've not got any metrics in place yet
what do you do the first thing is to
pick four or five key metrics to track
accurately not 30 or 50 four or five is
fine this number will grow over time
we'll talk about what those key metrics
should be in eight a little bit you
should pick the most straightforward
analytics solution you can operate it
might just be uh your SQL database
making simple SQL queries to count to
the number of signups post hog from
Winter 2020 has a great SQL Analytics
tool you can use on top of pretty much
any SQL database so you should check
that out you should also agree the
definitions of these four or five key
metrics and stick with them so it might
not be the absolute perfect definition
of an active user but constant arguments
about what your key metrics are are even
worse than having no metrics at all so
your whole team has to come together and
agree that an active user is someone who
uses the product every day or at least
once a week or at least five times a
week it honestly matters matters less
the precise definition than you actually
all agree with it I've remember so many
disagreements where the marketing team
said you know we've sent you 2,500 New
Leads this month and the sales team says
no no no they weren't qualified leads
they don't meet our definitions and this
disagreement internally just destroys
the productivity of meetings where
metrics are involved so you really have
to have centralized definitions of
metrics that are written down and
everyone agrees on so say you launched
and perhaps the metrics aren't quite
what you hoped the weekly active users
aren't quite as high as you you
originally wanted in that situation
Founders are often tempted to pick a
different metric or change the
definition of those metrics so instead
of a weekly active let's go for a
monthly active the number looks a bit
better honestly you're only fooling
yourself in this situation it's really
really important that you keep the
definition of your metric consistent
over time to see if you're improving or
not that's why it's so hard to compare
metrics between different companies
definition just vary so a weekly active
user at my company monzo was someone who
transacted who made a financial
transaction at least once a week an
active user at some of our competitors
used different definitions maybe it was
every two weeks or eight weeks and so
this active us account between companies
just became totally meaningless just
important that you keep it internally
consistent so you're keeping a good
track of it so now let's talk about what
those key metrics are those four or five
you should really start tracking from
early on it will vary from every company
back in the early days of the internet
companies like to use metrics like page
views or unique visitors or something
like that because they're really really
big numbers and startup Founders love to
report really big numbers you've
probably heard the term vanity metrics
these are numbers that seem really
really big and perhaps they keep
increasing they're not actually tied to
the success of your company more
recently common vanity metrics are
things like gmv or gross merchandise
value that's the total dollar value of
goods that are sold on eBay rather than
eBay's Revenue itself or gross
transaction value for a fintech like
monzo you could report we're transacting
$50 billion do a year it sounds like a
really really big number but the revenue
that the company makes can be very very
different and so almost always
especially for B2B companies your key
metric should be Revenue if you pick
another number take gross transaction
value you'll find that your employees
and eventually you might might start
optimizing for that number I worked with
a Neo Bank a couple of batches ago in
the Middle East and they were reporting
gross transaction value and they're very
very happy they came to every group
office hours and their gross transaction
value was growing 50% every two weeks it
looked really great and we scratched
beneath the surface a little bit and it
turned out that they were signing up
much much bigger customers who had
higher transaction value but giving them
massive cash back massive rebates to
transact on the platform so whilst gross
transaction value was Rising every two
week weeks Revenue actually was pretty
flat for about the last two months the
founders were tricking themselves they
were fooling themselves into thinking
their company was succeeding when in
fact it was pretty flat in Revenue terms
so revenue is the key metric I would
suggest for most B2B companies and don't
hide if your Revenue isn't good one of
the most impressive Founders I've ever
worked with sent 10 successive monthly
investor update emails with zero with a
big zero as the main metric at the top
of the emailed she kept herself honest
she was honest with investors and it
became clear what they needed to focus
on to fix the company so if you ashamed
of this number you hide it away it's
easy to kid yourself but I think if you
put it up front and Central and pay
attention to it it's the right thing to
focus on so two other key metrics
especially for investor updates
alongside your Revenue please include
burn rate that should be net what that
means is monthly costs minus your
revenues if you're loss making which
most early startups are it's the amount
by which your bank balance decreases
every month that is your burn rate and
your Runway is a function of that so say
you have a million dollar in the bank
and your burn rate is $100,000 a month
that means you have 10 months Runway
that means in 10 months you're going to
run out of money and the the startup
will be bankrupt those three numbers
Revenue burn rate and Runway are
absolutely crucial to include and if
they're not at the top of your investor
updates honestly I always uh assume this
founder has something to hide for
Consumer companies we have a separate
video diving deep into the metrics that
are important for those kind of startups
and often revenue is very important but
for the earliest days of consumer
companies often you're trying to get
some kind of critical mass or network
effect and so growing the active user
base in the early days for a consumer
company might in some cases be more
important than Revenue so we've talked
about the main three metrics that should
be at the top of every investor update
that's Revenue burn rate and Runway now
we're going to dive a little bit deeper
one of the most important metrics for
all startups really is retention this is
the idea that if you sign up a 100
paying customers say you sign them up in
January how many are still paying you in
February March and April two months 3
months four months later that's your
retention rate so it might be 80% or 70%
it's a sign that people love your
product they keep coming back and they
keep paying for it so you can measure it
for all customers who signed up in
January and the subsequent months and
that's your January cohort and then you
measure the same for all of the
customers who signed up in February
that's your February cohort and you can
stack these cohorts on top of each other
and there are a number of different ways
of graphing this you might have a heat
map and some analytics tools do this
really nicely you might have a curve
that sort of decays over time those are
two pretty common ways of graphing it
and we'll show some examples but I'd
like to suggest a third way this is is
when it really clicked for me I'd heard
everyone tell me that Revenue was really
really important but it only really
clicked for me after I worked at a
dating startup that actually had very
bad retention and ultimately failed
sadly but it clicked when I stacked
these cohorts on top of each other so
you see the January cohort at the bottom
and then the February cohort and then
the March cohort and the April cohort
and what happens if you have sticky
cohorts if your retention is really high
you know 80 90 100% is you cohorts stay
really fat over time and you build up
this layer cake so you can imagine what
happens two or three years later if you
have dozens of these monthly cohorts
stacked on top of each other they're all
paying you money they're all
contributing to your Revenue every
single month even three years later and
if you're in a low churn business it
adds up to a layer cake that looks
something like this so this is an
18month graph of monthly cohorts each
month you're adding a new layer on and
after 18 months you've got 18 cohorts
still paying you this was like my first
company go cardless it was a a recurring
payments company very similar to stripe
and with those kind of companies people
Implement a payment solution once they
don't really like to change it every
month there's a lot of effort so the
customers are very very sticky and you
can imagine the team at go cardless goes
on holiday you know for a month after 18
months and the revenue stays pretty
consistent the beauty is actually
expanding Revenue so if those customers
you signed up in January launch grow
with the company they're using goard or
stripe as a payment processor they're
transacting more volume in year two and
year three they're growing their
business the revenue for for strip or go
carders actually increases as well so
the team perhaps goes on holiday or
signs up no new customers the business
still grows Revenue that's the beauty of
this this High retention business it's
sort of growing constantly underneath
you you're adding these layers and
layers and layers of Revenue and
eventually become Unstoppable but that
only happens if your retention flattens
out at some point if these Decay curves
flatten at some point and it almost
matters that they flatten out at any
point as opposed to a high point you
know I I take a 20% retention that
flattens out over a higher retention
initially that goes to zero because if
you sign up 100 people in January and by
month three or month six they've all
churn off they've all stopped paying you
get a very different layer cake that
lovely flat layer cake that builds up
and up over time if your customers all
churn out looks like this so you can see
customers you sign up in month one by
month three have more or less gone and
let's fast forward to month six they've
all gone by month 9 or month 10 and so
rather than building up secure and
steadfast layers month after month
you're actually scrambling to fill up a
leaky bucket you're pouring water into
the top of the bucket and it's leaking
out of the bucket just as fast as you
can fill it up you can imagine this is
an impossible task and so if your
business has customers that that don't
retain where retention goes to zero
you'll reach some natural Plateau where
you're working as hard as you can to
fill up the customers who simply churned
out last month and it's very very hard
to build a big business like that it's a
futile Endeavor so we talked about
overall retention number of customers
for B2B startups people often talk about
net dollar retention this is just a
fancy way of calculating retention
mostly used in B2B SAS companies so
let's take an example we've started an
AI customer service chatbot very uh
invogue at the moment and say we we sign
up 10 paying customers in January in the
first month and they're each paying
$10,000 a month so 10K Mr each you're at
100K of monthly recurring Revenue feels
pretty good right let's fast forward a
year and in each of those subsequent
months you'll have signed up more
customers let's let's ignore them for
now focus on those 10 initial customers
you signed up in January but fast
forward 12 months perhaps two of those
customers have canceled their contracts
at some point in the year so we're down
to
$80,000 of monthly revenue from that
cohort but you've also upsold three
customers perhaps you've introduced some
new functionality or they've they're
using it more and instead of paying
10,000 they're each paying 20,000
perhaps you do phone chat as well as
text chat so that's $30,000 of
additional Revenue so we've lost 20 but
gained 30 so that's net 10K plus so
$110,000 of monthly revenue from that
January cohort that's why it's called
net dollar retention it's the amount
you've gained that's netted off against
the amount you've lost so that cohort
that was making $100,000 at the start in
January of year one a year later January
of year two is making a
$110,000 that's equivalent to 110% net
dollar retention so a net dollar
retention above 100% means your cohorts
are growing over time if your net dollar
attention is below 100% they're
shrinking over time youve got to pour
more water into the funnel to fill up
the the Leaky buckets we talked about
and that's what gives very sticky
businesses like stripe like go carders
like PayPal this exponential growth it's
adding new customers every month but
having existing customers grow
underneath them as well and that gives
you this exponential growth curve that's
very very impressive the final thing as
a benchmark any early stage B2B SAS
company should be looking at net dollar
retention well above 100% this is for
several reasons first of all you've
probably underpriced your product with
your first launch so you might charge
$10,000 a month for your initial
customers you realize pretty quickly uh
that the product could be sold for 20 or
$30,000 secondly you're adding features
the whole time presumably you're
improving your product and so that makes
it more appealing and customers are
willing to pay more money thirdly you
should be getting it better at sales and
upselling over time as well it' be weird
if you weren't getting better at that
and so those three reasons net dollar
retention for early stage B2B startup
should be 125% 150% would be great even
higher than that for mature companies uh
in the same range 110% 120% is pretty
good net dollar attention if your net
dollar attention is below 100%
especially for Enterprise B2B SAS
something is wrong you are churning off
customers they don't love the product
and I would invest in fixing that
talking to customers and figuring out
why they're turning off rather than
trying to to shove more customers in the
top of the funnel by investing in sales
and marketing for example net dollar
retention is absolutely crucial for B2B
SAS companies okay the second Deep dive
we're going to do on B2B metrics and
this is applicable to Consumer companies
as well is gross margin gross margin is
your Revenue the money you get from
customers minus the cost of goods sold
so you can imagine that if you're a
grocery store that's most obvious you're
selling you're selling sandwiches for
example the cost of good sold is the
cost of the bread and the cost of the
butter and the the filling that goes in
the sandwich that's cost of good sold
for a software company it's any cost
that varies per customer or for each
incremental customer you incur more cost
so let's go back to example we had
earlier we were running a an AI customer
service bot and you're probably using
something like open AI or anthropic to
power the core model behind that and so
the cost the credits that you pay to
open AI or anthropic or someone else is
your cost of goods sold we didn't used
to talk about this very much for B2B SAS
companies because the cost of goods was
very very minimal for Pure software it
might have been your AWS bill or your
bandwidth bill or something like that
it's minimal and so pure B2B SAS
companies in the past might have had
gross margins of 95% you know you sell
$100 worth of software and it's only $5
of cost and so people just assume it's
very very high margin but these days as
software sort of taking over more and
more Industries gross margin has become
more and more important so for AI
companies today the gross margin the
amount they pay to open AI or anthropic
or others for the foundation model is a
really important cost and by the way
just because you're getting free credits
doesn't mean that that's a cost that
doesn't exist it just means you're
hiding it for the moment so companies
that hide behind open AI credits and
claim that they've got these huge huge
gross margins have a nasty shock coming
when those credits run out it's also why
heavily operational businesses are so
tricky and when a company joins YC with
a with something like a grocery delivery
business or really any kind of business
where a lot of humans involved a lot of
operational processes going along you
maybe you paint houses or install heat
pumps or something you have to pay a lot
more attention to the gross margin
because it's very rare that it's as high
as 95% you might be down at 5 10 15%
gross margins which means you have to do
a lot more work you have to get a lot
more customers a lot more Revenue to
generate the same gross margin and that
gross margin is the thing that can then
pay your head office rent your
engineering salaries all of those
remaining costs that don't vary per
customer but still have to be deducted
before you get to profitability and so
for operationally intensive businesses
we often try to work with Founders to
see if there's a software only version
of their business that they can run at a
much higher margin so for example
instead of running a delivery company
where you have Vans and bikes and
and delivery people instead can you take
the software that powers all of that and
sell it to other delivery companies
you're going to have a probably a much
easier life certainly you're going to
have much higher gross margins if you do
that so in the zero interest rate
environment sort of 2010 to 2021 period
companies were scaling negative margin
businesses because Capital was so cheap
famously Uber did this they used capital
as a weapon so they took these
businesses that were initially negative
gross margin that means they're
effectively selling $10 worth of service
but only charging $9 so losing money on
every single order but trying to get to
a sort of a network effect or a Tipping
Point um for Uber famously it was a
certain number of drivers certain
density of drivers and riders in a
certain city that gets the flywheel
going but when they launched in a new
city they didn't have that density and
so they had to subsidize drivers and
subsidize Riders which made it a
negative gross margin business and so
they raised enormous amounts of capital
to expand across the globe before
competitors could catch up but burnt
tens of billions of dollars of invested
money in doing so and that Blitz scaling
approach that that scaling of negative
margin got popular with Founders and so
we saw it in ride sharing then we saw it
in 10-minute grocery delivery we saw it
with electric scooters and honestly
there's like a a whole Wasteland of
startups that tried to do that and then
realize they couldn't continue to raise
money as investors just didn't want to
keep subsidizing these businesses and
certainly now with much higher interest
rates Capital has become much more
expensive investors are really really
loed to invest in negative margin
businesses and it's much much harder to
scale those those negative margins we
did this at monzo so monzo was an online
bank in the UK and for our first half
million customers or so we were losing
money on every customer 30 or 40 per
customer customer we scale to more than
half a million of those customers it
costs a lot but we had a plan to turn it
around so we brought technology in house
we didn't rely so much on external
vendors we introduced charges for
certain things we introduced new
products that customers were happy to
pay for and over time we flipped those
negative unit economics so rather than
losing 30 or 40 pounds per customer we
ended up when I was there making 30 or
40 pound per customer and now three or
four years later monzo is profitable so
if if you start with negative unit
economics you really really have to have
a plan to fix them and I would really
advise you don't scale your customer
base you don't try and grow as quickly
as possible whilst you have negative
unit economics you fix them first and
then you scale pH we covered a lot of
stuff today so as a recap we talked
about revenue and why it's the best core
metric for most B2B companies then we
talked about retention and it's fancy
cousin net dollar retention and why
having a net dollar retention above 100%
is so important for B2B startups and we
finish with gross margin and why it's so
important not to scale businesses with
negative gross margins I wrap up with
some final thoughts make sure you're
tracking your four or five key metrics
before you launch don't launch without
metrics in place it's like Flying Blind
be rigorous in what you track track the
right metrics don't fall for vanity
metrics like gross merchandise value
your impressions or unique users have a
clear definition of each of your metrics
and a central way of measuring them in
your company to avoid those pointless
arguments that derails meetings don't
hide behind your metrics you can't split
everything especially as a small startup
so a lot of these decisions just have to
be made by talking to your users and
using your product intuition you still
have to get out of the building and talk
to customers that's so important so I
hope that helps run your startup with
the right blend of metrics talking to
customers and product intuition those
three are a vital blend thanks for
watching
[Music]
today